it's impossible to lift with all back
now for the past
30 years as a lifter i've been hearing
this in gyms it's one of my pet peeves
it always happens when you see uh
someone doing deadlifts
and they have a rounded back and you'll
hear someone
commenting on their form and they'll be
like dude you lifted with all back
bro bro bro you're lifting with all back
and while it's well intentioned because
they're usually trying to warn the
person like hey
you're using poor form it reflects an
inadequate
understanding of biomechanics the reason
why this came to be is because
when you round your back you're using
less legs and
you feel it more in your back but if we
break it down biomechanically
you'll see why this critique falls flat
now it is true that
lifting with a rounded back usually
involves less quad muscle
and you definitely feel it in your back
more interestingly
in the literature when you round your
back to lift something up
you use less erector spinae muscle now
the job of the erectors is to erect the
spine when you round you're not erecting
the spine
but there's something in the literature
known as the lumbar flexion relaxation
phenomenon and what it means is
essentially when you fully round the
erectors go silent
meaning they're not activated now they
still provide muscle force
due to passive stretch but it's not
activated
and you end up feeling it more in your
back just because
with a fully flexed spine you end up
putting more stress on the
intervertebral discs
and some of the ligaments now when
someone doesn't have good leg strength
i don't have good leg strength so i do
this
[Music]
you'll see them set up in a deadlift
everything looks good
they go to lift the bar off the ground
their hips shoot up their hips shoot up
they round their back around the back
and then all of a sudden you see
the bar come off the floor now what
they're doing is straightening their
legs out
rounding their back and turning it more
into a hamstring exercise
their quads can't do the job to lift the
weight up
so they shift it more to their
hamstrings now with a fully rounded back
we already talked about how you're using
less erector your knees straighten out
so you're going to use
less quad but you're still in deep hip
flexion
even when you round your back so much
and your spine is flexed you're still
in about the same amount of hip flexion
as with of deadlift with good form
so you have the same hip range of motion
either way but in a good deadlift you
have
more knee range of motion and less
spinal range of motion
and in a poor deadlift you have more
spinal range of motion and less knee
range of motion
so let's say i fully round over and i
touch my toes
okay i keep my legs as straight as
possible and i touch my toes
all right if i just erect my spine
from a fully rounded over position and i
erect my spine
i will raise the barbell 12 inches but
my overall range of motion
is 28 inches so the remaining 16 inches
is all hip extension i'm in deep hip
flexion and i have to extend the hips
the spinal erectors
cannot extend the hips the only thing
that can extend the hips are the
hamstrings the adductors and the gluteus
maximus
in other words you have to use your
hippic sensors you have to use your
glutes
hamstrings and adductors even in a
crappy deadlift
so when someone says dude that was all
back in their minds they think it was
all erectors
and your leg muscles are just silent and
that's not true you have to use leg
muscles
to pick weight off the floor and stand
up with it yes you'll feel it more in
your back
when you round over when you round over
more
thus compressive forces can wreak havoc
on the discs
especially with very very heavy
deadlifts so ideally you'd be mostly
neutral
with deadlifts now i don't think i'm
going to change gym culture that's been
around for like 30 years
actually i don't even know when this
came to be because it was this was being
said when i was 15 years old
i mean honestly my good bro i was
checking out your deadlift pattern and
while you move a lot of weight
your patterning could use a little bit
of work you need to drop the hips arch
the back more
use the legs more and quit rounding your
back so much
you're not going to hear them be
accurate biomechanically but you still
shouldn't say you're lifting with all
back because even when you
you take the ugliest deadlift like type
in deadlift fail videos onto youtube
you'll see
these people like fully rounded over you
know convulsing and
uh with these terribly ugly deadlifts
they're still using a lot of hamstrings
they're not using a lot of quads but
they are using a lot of hamstrings
and glutes just to stand up their
erectors even though it looks like
they're using all back
ironically the erectors are silent as i
talked about earlier
at least not nearly as activated as if
they were using good form if you keep an
arch
and you deadlift a lot of weight you're
using a lot more active muscle force
in the spinal directors so yes this is
just
me kind of like showing off my
biomechanical knowledge
it's not going to matter much i just
wanted to point out uh that this is a
pet peeve of mine and i hope
some of you appreciate the
technicalities i hope some of you
like learning about the biomechanics
because i've got a lot more knowledge to
share
so if you like this make sure you
comment subscribe to my channel
hit like i'm going to keep coming out
with videos every week
so stay tuned for more now if you like
what you see here and you want to train
using my principles under my system
please click on the link below
and subscribe to booty by brett and join
the thousands of other happy members who
are seeing incredible results
you